Never forget why you are the church.
ahead and turn your Bibles to Revelation 8.
Revelation 8.
That's what will be tonight.
We're continuing our study of the end times.
And we're going to begin finally to
look at the 7 trumpet starting in Revelation 8.
Now, let me just kind of give you a kind of some insight on how this study is going.
Because I know it seems like I say what
we're going to do and then we get stuck on, you know, a very nuanced
topic and then we have a whole message on that and then we don't get to what we said.
Here's how I'm doing this, just for full transparency.
Each week, I look at Revelation, I
look at where we're at, kind of in the timeline, and I say, Lord, what do we need to know?
And then he shows me.
And then I preach it.
Is that fair enough?
So when I'm when I'm studying in Revelation, and I see the 144,000, and I see, you
know, the multitude, and I see some of these things that simply, you know, maybe confusing or maybe
people don't understand it or maybe it's it's not understandable, right?
We need to know that.
And so I'm not necessarily, this is not as clean cut as
just the next thing in line in Romans on Sunday mornings.
So I just kind of wanted to make that.
Because my plan for the last month has been the get to where we are tonight and it just hasn't happened.
But we are actually going to look at the Trumpets tonight, okay?
And so again, the last 2 weeks.
We have taken a deep dive into the 144,000.
who they were and what was their purpose during a tribulation.
And I pray that we were on mission here
on earth now, just as they will be on mission then during a tribulation.
In other words, their sole purpose was to see as many people come to know Jesus as possible.
We may not be in the great tribulation, but you need to hear me.
People are dying and going to hell every single day.
They're not even making it to the tribulation, but they're going to eternal torment.
That ought to prick our hearts in such a way.
We have an urgency to share the gospel.
Amen?
And so we need to understand that.
Whenever we talk about eschatology.
Whenever we talk about the end times, I understand that
depending on your eschatological view, you may be here, you may not be here.
Listen, I'm midair.
Whenever, if I'm here, that stinks.
If I'm not here, praise the Lord.
Does that make sense?
I'm not one of these Christians like, man, bring me to the tribulation.
No, Lord, take me up, right?
I don't want to be here when that happens.
But either way, either way.
What we do now is more important than something we don't actually know for sure.
We know that something is going to happen.
We know that we have details.
We don't know exactly when, but we do know that people need to know Jesus now today.
Amen?
And so that's really what our eschatology should bring us to.
Our mission is to lead as many of the crisis.
Remember, we're to love others unconditionally, learn about God increasingly, live to share Jesus intentionally.
Why?
So we can lead others to Christ continually in Lebanon, Tennessee, and throughout the whole world.
Okay?
So we're in Revelation 8, and we don't have to read all of it, okay?
It's actually a short, short little chapter.
And so you can go home and read that in your reading today.
But the title that we're going to look at is God's wrath announced and active.
God's wrath announced and active.
You're in Revelation eight.
We'll read here in just a second.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you, Lord, for this night.
I thank you for your word.
God, I thank you for your wisdom and discernment, God, and knowledge that you give us.
So God, I pray that no matter what, we put our faith in you
and in you alone, God, because you're worthy of it all.
So speak through me tonight, since Jesus name, pray.
anybody said?
Amen, if you remember several weeks back, we went over in
detail verses 3 through 5 regarding the angel who filled the censor with the fire of
the altar and prayers of the saints and cast it upon
the earth just to give you a quick review of that in verse 3 and another angel came.
I believe this is a different angel than the 7 with the trumpets.
And he stood at the altar having a golden sensor, and there was given
unto him much incense that he should offer it with the
prayers of all the saints upon the golden altar which before the throne.
And the smoke of the incense, which came with the prayers of the saints, ascended up before God out of the angel's hand.
And the angel took the censer and filled it with the fire of the altar
and cast it into the earth, and there were voices and thunderings and lightnings and earthquake.
So again, we went over this, not going to be talking about this,
but the message of that is, understand that the
prayer, the prayers of the saints are precious to God.
Nothing you ever pray leaves him.
Nothing you ever pray gets past him, gets around him.
He is just, he is, he is big enough to
be able to hear all of our prayers and evidently he takes our prayers and he keeps them because they're precious.
Aren't you glad that we have such a loving God?
Isn't that awesome?
So that's, again, we're going to kind of move on from that.
So I want to look at Revelation 8, verse one.
It says this.
And when he had opened the 7 seal, There was silence in heaven.
about the space of a half an hour.
Now, what an odd detail and occurrence we see here.
But there is more to this when you realize what
is actually taking place before and after this 30 minutes of silence.
Again, John tells us for 30 minutes, there was complete silence in heaven.
This must have been an intensely dramatic
and mesmerizing time for John, but why, by the way, you do know silence speaks very loudly.
Amen?
Have you ever been in a loud room, having
a loud conversation, then all of a sudden everyone else goes quiet, but you're
still being loud and you're like, ooh, that's awkward.
Right?
Silence can get you into a spot.
But what do we know about heaven thus far?
What is happening in heaven before this 30 minutes?
Well, the living creatures?
The elders and all the angels.
Think about it, without ceasing up to this point, have praised and worshiped God from the beginning of their creation.
Literally, the volume in heaven has been on 10 for a long, long, long time.
Then all of a sudden, the lamb,
that is, Jesus Christ breaks the 7 seal, which reveals
the 7 trumpets and all the voices, all the praise, all the instruments, all the shouting stops.
Something different is about to happen.
Something new is going to take place.
May I remind you how the Bible describes the time of the Great Tribulation in Matthew 24, verse 21,
For then there will be a great tribulation, such has not
occurred since the beginning of the world until now, nor ever will.
In other words, we're about to see something that
has never happened and will never have to happen again.
Some people differentiate the seals from the Trumpets, Trumpets.
In other words, they would call the great tribulation.
The 7 year span is called
the tribulation, but when we get to the 7 trumpets,
they call that the part of the tribulation, that's the great
tribulation, because the intensity of God's wrath gets turned up quite a bit.
Again, here we see an uptick in judgment.
There must have been something to this because the 30 minute pause is almost a divine understanding.
an acknowledgement of what is about to occur.
It's almost like a moment of silence for what is about to take place on the earth.
As I thought about this, I got to thinking.
Is it possible?
And listen, I love I love looking at scripture of what is to come.
I love looking at scripture what has already been, but
I need you to understand that we can take principles and truth
from God's word and just about every page and apply it to our life and obedience here.
Now, I'm not saying it's always a clean cut thing.
We don't ever want to impose in a text, but as I was thinking about
this silence, is it possible that your lack of praise shows more than you realize.
Just hang with me for a moment.
I know he put a lot of weight in the vocal and audible praise
of God, some of my favorite times of our worship
team, leading worship is when they come off the mic,
that it's almost like they even come off the guitars, and man,
in those precious times to where they just let the people worship.
They get to just worship off the mic and it's almost like
the volume intensity kind of goes up from that point, right?
We put a lot of stalking when we worship.
It is an audible form of praise.
Especially in the corporate gathering of the saints.
Now, I'm not on, I'm on record for saying this is not a personality thing.
Well, my personality isn't cohesive with worship, pastor.
Well, then you need to change your stinking personality.
Amen?
You understand what I'm saying?
Listen, you just told on yourself.
There's something in everyone's life they are willing to get loud about.
You know, whether it be sports or politics or a successful day at work, whatever it may be, right?
You get that big sale, right?
You get done with the yard after a hot day and you give a big old shout,
like there's something that gets you loud and vocal in your life.
I cannot imagine God sitting the elders and the angels down and asking them.
Now, before we get to, before we get to our our
eternal choir session, I just need to ask you, what is your preferred form of worship?
Hey, man.
Could you imagine one of the, y'all doing what you do?
You're just staring at me like, listen,
yeah, me and to you, you know what I'm saying?
But listen, think about it.
Sit him down and say, look, hey, or God, you know, I'd love to be in the choir, but, you know, I just, I
like to just kind of sing to myself and do this,
and, you know, I'm not really one to get kind of loud and stuff.
Okay, well, you're not in a choir anymore, bud.
You gotta go somewhere else.
No, that's not what happens.
Everyone that was a part of this.
They had no shame in the fact that they're worshiping the king and they were loud about it.
You say, well, does it really matter?
Well, I mean, again, whatever gets you loud, if it's not the Lord, then it could be an idol.
But they simply praised him emphatically without ceasing around the throne.
All I'm saying here is that we do not ever see them stop praising God outside of this moment.
Now, I know we go through things that are heavy and difficult in our lives.
And I'll be honest with you, there's times to where I sit.
I did on this past Sunday.
I sat there, I had my head down.
I was praying with tears coming through my eyes because of just the
weight of the truth that we were singing and just the gospel impact of my life.
Listen, I'm not saying that we can't we can't do that.
All I'm trying to say is that we better have a heart posture of worship no matter what's going on.
But again, to get back to the text.
That was just a little commercial for you.
Nothing compares to this moment we see about take place in Revelation 8.
Again, the point, praise him, praise him loud.
And you say, well, that sounds like preference theology.
I'm just seeing a pattern here in scripture that whenever we see someone praising the Lord, it's loud.
It's vocal.
Now, there's also a 30 minute pause in the worship,
so we see in Revelation verse eight, two, it says or
chapter 8, verse two, and I saw the 7 angels which stood before God, and to them were given 7 trumpets.
Now, it may be a natural thought to think that these are trumpets as in the instrument, right?
And if you just look at it just from the, from the, just the obvious thing,
and, okay, they had trumpets, like, like that you would play, and that's what we're talking about.
But there's actually, if you look at how scripture is
written in all the things that goes into it, there's no reason to believe that these are 7 literal trumpets.
Rather, God is using imagery from the Old Testament.
See, in the Old Testament, it used apocalyptic tradition, trumpets were used as a signal of divine judgment and intervention.
In other words, when you heard trumpets.
It was there was some judgment coming, right?
The enemy was at your door or you were blowing
the trumpets and you were at the enemy's door and you were therefore judging the enemy.
That's what the Old Testament imagery is all about.
By the way, where do we see this in the Old Testament?
Well, this is pretty cool right here because everything connects.
You remember Joshua?
Remember Joshua in the Bible, a whole book with his name on it, right?
Joshua.
Listen, he took over leadership of Israel after Moses died.
They finally crossed the Jordan, and the 1st
enemy city that God put on their sites to conquer was Jericho.
Now I want you to think about this for a second.
The 1st enemy city that
God put in their sights just so happened, I mean, the most fortified,
largest impenetrable city in the promised land.
It was almost as if God's saying, hey, listen, we're here.
Let's go get them.
And so they see Jericho, and as
a matter of fact, don't want you to know that Jericho is believed to be the
oldest continuously inhabited city in the entire world.
Even to this day, there is a city where Jericho is, college Jericho, Jericho does.
And it is a thriving city of 20,000 residents.
I thought that was pretty cool.
But in the time of Joshua, Jericho is seemingly impossible to conquer.
So how did God use the Israelites to conquer such an awesome city?
Well, I told you it was cool.
So this is where it gets cool.
His instruction was very specific.
For 6 days, the men of war, fully dressed in battle array, with 7 priests bearing the Ark
of the Covenant, walked around the city once.
They did that one time each day for 6 days.
Joshua 6, verse 10, but Joshua commanded the
people saying, you shall not shout, nor let your voice
be heard, nor let a word proceed out of your mouth until
the day I tell you shout, then you shall shout.
So stand out for a second.
I don't know.
That'd be kind of hard for me.
I'd probably have to stay home for that one, you know what I'm saying?
But they had to literally walk around Jericho and they were completely signed.
We say, well, what was it, just science?
No, no, no, no.
The only sound that was made was the trumpets of ram's horn, the priest used.
In other words, while they were walking that lap, the
priest in the front, they were blowing the horns,
blowing the trumpets while everyone else was in silence.
So you were hearing trumpets and you were hearing the marching of God's army.
By the way, could you imagine this seeing an entire army of men of valor in war walking around the walls?
The only sound that was heard was the sound of the trumpets.
What the people of Jericho did not understand that the
sound they were hearing was incoming judgment.
Remember, divine intervention.
But on the 7th day, they would circle the city 7 times.
And at the end of the 7th lap, the priest would give a long, powerful trumpet sound, and
at that point, the men of war who had been silent for the last 7 days.
They gave a big shout.
It was here that the walls crumbled around Jericho, and God's judgment was had on the city.
Now again, I don't know about you, but I think it's pretty cool.
that John used Old Testament, divine judgment and intervention symbolism
with the trumpets, and you look at one of the one
of the most known stories in the Old Testament, Jericho, they were silent all 6 days, but then
now the 7th day at the 7th lap, they shouted and the walls crumbled down.
Isn't God awesome in his word?
I mean, we're talking about from Joshua to Revelation here.
So we see throughout the scripture that the Old Testament used trumpets, again, as a sign of judgment.
Zephan I called this day a day of trumpet and alarm.
Zephaniah 116, a day of the trumpet and alarm against
the fenced cities and against the high towers.
Jesus speaks to this time as like a sound of a trumpet when he calls his people up.
He will send forth his angels, a great trumpet, and they will gather together his elect
from the 4 winds, from the one end of the sky to the other.
We see here the trumpets are used as markers of God's decisive action throughout history.
And in the great tribulation, it is no different.
So what we see here is the announcements of God's wrath upon the earth.
that become active.
So what did these announcements entail?
The scroll has been unraveled.
What does it say?
Well, let's look at the 1st trumpet, shall we?
since we set the table.
Look at verses 6 or starting in verse six.
If you're there to say, I'm there.
Good, good, good.
It says this, and his 7 angels, which had the 7 trumpets, prepared themselves to sound.
The 1st angel sound and there followed hell on fire and mingled
with blood, and they were cast upon the earth, and the 3rd part of the tree
was burnt up and all the green grass was burnt.
Up.
Now this one is dreadfully straightforward.
God will send such a storm, the world has never seen a
phenomenon that can only be divine judgment from God.
Hail.
And fire, which are opposites, by the way.
I don't know if you know that in iron.
you know, you got ice, you got fire.
Hail and fire mixed with blood will be poured upon the earth.
We see this actually foretold in Joel chapter 2, verse 30.
I will display wonders in the sky and on the earth, blood, fire, and columns of smoke.
And the results are devastating.
One 3rd of the trees are burned up and all the grass is burned out.
This completely changes the landscape and dynamic of the earth.
Why is this such an issue?
What would this change?
Well, if you took a 3rd of the trees from the earth, severe soil erosion would begin.
This would speed up because the grass was also gone.
The water cycles would be completely disrupted.
Oxygen would begin to become less and less available.
Air pollution would be at an all time high.
There would be agricultural collapse.
Another catastrophic problem that some may not see coming is if you take a 3rd of the trees out.
You're going to take probably a 3rd of the animal kingdom out that
live within the trees and within the trees and all the things.
We have no idea how bad this is going to be, and it's just the start.
of the 7 trumpets.
I do want to point out that a 4th of the population has already
been killed during the break into the 4th seal in Revelation 6.
So we're seeing utter and complete devastation on the earth right here.
But then we get to the 2nd trumpet.
Revelation 8, verse 8 and 9 says this,
and the 2nd angel sounded, and as it were, a great mountain
burning when fire was cast into the sea, and the 3rd part of the sea became blood.
And the 3rd part of the creatures which were in the sea and had life died
and the 3rd part of the ships were destroyed.
Notice John is using less specific language here.
The NASB 95 makes this more clear.
The 2nd angel sounded in something like a great
mountain burning with fire was thrown into the sea, and a 3rd of the sea became blood.
Now remember, we can read in a literal way when we should.
When we can, we should, but where we can't, we ought not to.
Something like a great mountain burning when fire was thrown into the sea.
It could be fun to speculate this.
Is this talking about nuclear warfare?
Is this talking about some kind of, you know, meteorite, whatever it is?
what in the world is this?
We don't know.
We just know what the effects of it were.
Not only do we not know exactly what it is and how it happened.
We know who sent it and that's God through his judgment.
But the effects of the Great Burning Mountain.
Like thing is great.
A 3rd of the sea became blood.
Notice it doesn't say light blood, but became blood.
So I don't believe it's a symbolic at all.
You say, how in the world could this happen?
Well, a 3rd of the creatures in the sea dies in a 3rd of the ships in the sea are destroyed.
Now let's think about this for a moment.
I kind of went, I kind of went, I turn into a nerd here for a 2nd as I was putting this together.
The estimated, they estimate scientists that are a lot smarter than me.
estimate of the total ocean, the total
ocean life varies between 300,000, and this is this is where science.
Listen, If you put all your stock in science, that is a sad, sad way to live.
Because it is so variable, you know what I'm saying?
You put your stock in the Lord because he's the way, the truth, and life.
You know what I'm saying?
Like you can just trust what's going on.
He says it's going to happen, it's going to happen, exactly how it says.
But listen to this stat right here.
Between 300,000 and 2200000 different species.
Well, that, to me, seems like a pretty vast number
of, you know, 300,000 is a lot less than two.
Okay, y'all aren't with me.
Some scientists estimate.
There are 30000000 creatures in the sea.
Now, that kind of surprised me.
I thinking, man, the sea's pretty big because the sea means ocean in this in this situation.
So all the seas, oceans, all of it.
But here's the kicker.
These numbers are only a starting point because 90% of the oceans and the life in the oceans have not even been discovered.
So we're talking about some massive destruction from this 2nd trumpet.
Do you realize the magnitude of 13rd of these creatures dying?
I did the math.
Just one blue whale has 1400 gallons of blood circulating in his body at all times.
That's the biggest whale in the animal kingdom of the whale kingdom, whatever you want to call it.
Okay?
1400 gallons.
First off, that's absolutely disgusting.
But with a high number of 25,000 blue
whales, right, there used to be 300,000, then you had the whale market and they killed them down all things.
But I took a high number of 25,000 blue whales, which was the high
number they said could be in the world right now.
A 3rd of those whales can produce over 11500000
gallons of blood, and that's just one species.
In addition to that, there are 1000000s and 1000000s of boats and
ships in the water at any given time, and a 3rd are destroyed.
With the 1st trumpet burning up the trees and grass, could it be that maybe
we're forced to, as people, to try to go to the sea,
to fish and to have sustenance there, and then
before you know it, they're all destroyed as well.
No wonder a 3rd of the seas turned to blood.
There's that much death.
Now, you might be thinking, well, at least we have our freshwater sources.
All right, at least we have our homestead.
Listen, I'm all about some homestead.
You know, I grew some sunflowers this year.
You ever grow some sun?
What you laughing about, Herman?
She laugh at that.
Sunflassic Garden, okay?
I put a seed in the ground and it sprouted up something.
It was a living organism.
That's called a gardener farmer, okay?
So either way, so this, but here's how bad I am at planting sunflowers.
I'm planning about a 20 foot row of them.
4 popped up.
Okay?
Not only did 4 out of a 20 foot row pop up, every single one of the four.
4 for 4 is facing my fence and not facing the house where I can see them.
So all I see is just the back of a sunflower.
That may not be the pressing to you, but it's pretty upsetting to me, okay?
But what I'm trying to say is this.
What about the fresh water source?
It's okay.
I don't know.
I have a Burkey at home.
Anyone know what a Burkie is?
Man, you can put creek water in that thing and drink it.
Now I don't want to, but if I ever had to, I could.
You understand what I'm saying?
But what happens with the fresh water?
Okay?
That brings us to the next trumpet.
Revelation 8, 10 and 11.
And the 3rd angel sounded, and there fell a great star from heaven, burning as it were a lamp.
And it fell upon the 3rd part of the rivers and upon the fountains of waters.
There goes your fresh water sources.
And the name of a star is called wormwood.
And the 3rd part of the waters became wormwood, and many
men died of the waters because they were made bitter.
You see here some kind of meteoric mass that falls to the earth.
Could this be the, by the way, as I was looking at this and studying this,
some equate this to the sensor that the angel cast upon the earth as part of the judgment.
I don't know that for sure, but it is an interesting thought.
All we know is that when it hits the earth, it falls upon a 3rd
of the rivers and upon the fountains of water.
The fountains of water speaks, the wells deep within the earth that we get our water from.
Now, I want to think about something here.
With the trees and grass affected like they already have been.
Waters begin to dry up anyway.
Right?
If you ever want to make a desert, you take away the grass, you take away the trees.
That's how you get a desert.
You ever been in the desert and see a forest?
No, because there's a desert there.
Amen?
Okay?
So, so, so in reality, these water sources are not as thriving as they are now anyway.
By the way, we can't even handle the water situation in Lebanon, let alone the whole world.
So think about the catastrophic situation we're going to have here.
And then you take a 3rd of them and poison them.
We see the star's name is wormwood in botany,
a wormwood is a shrub like plant noted for its extreme bitterness and poisonous properties.
What is the result?
It is so bitter.
It is so poisonous that many men die.
You can't go to the seas because a thought of his blood.
You can't you can't go to the woods because a 3rd of them are gone.
You can't go to the river, the whales because they're poisoned.
3rd of one's poison.
You see, you see the judgment God has put upon the earth.
Church, none of this has happened yet.
But it will.
This is why it's so important to know Jesus.
Amen?
Not only do you get the joy and the victory and forgiveness that comes
with salvation, but you can be saved, the Bible says from the wrath to come.
There has been no wrath like there will be.
in a tribulation.
So as we continue to break this trumpets or judgment announcements down in
the next coming weeks, I don't want to do this to cause you fear.
But I do believe that we need to know what's going to happen.
By the way, I grew up
under a preacher that man, he could preach Revelation.
I'm talking.
He'd have you crying, scared, hiding under the pew, man.
I mean, I'm talking Brother Glenn, he would just, it was a whole nother situation.
And I always remember as a kid being scared to death every time Revelation was preached.
And I knew wise because I knew that that I was lost.
And there was a chance that I could be here when this is happening.
And if I can't profess Jesus' Lord now.
What makes me think I'll be able to then.
In my comfort and in my convenience and in my, I got a roof over my head.
Listen, it rain, then it stormed last night.
Y'all, was that did that happen at your house too?
As a matter of fact, Mike is right now, he's helping a family,
a tree literally fell and hit both cars in the driveway.
Like, like done.
It was like the chaos commercial with the guy that like, you
know, gets thrown around and say, you want to see that one, the insurance commercial, you know what I'm talking about?
Okay, I'm glad I have normal people in my congregation.
Some of y'all are like, I don't watch TV.
Hank Hartler.
But listen, hey, I mean, just, you know, we sit here and I used to be so scared.
But then you think, if I can't with the shelter over my head, with the
food in my pantry, with the water, I have a filter in my in
my refrigerator and I can get ice and I can get water anytime I want.
If that runs out, I can put tap water in a burkey, I can get, you
know, all these conveniences we have, yet our passion for Christ is not where it should be.
Listen, hey, if you're lost and you go to the tribulation,
Don't count on giving your life to Christ, Dan.
The Bible even says it's going to be a strong delusion given to those.
And so today's the day of grace.
And so if this scares you.
I'm not here to scare you, but I do think that fear exposes.
So if this scares you, hey, listen, why?
Why?
If this used to cause me fear for myself, but now, you know what it does?
It causes me fear for everybody else.
When I think about the loved ones I have, don't know Jesus.
God forbid they have to go through this.
So what does that do?
I want to share the gospel.
So again, there's 2 things that I want us to have.
other than fear.
Number one, an appreciation for Jesus.
and the deliverance and protection he gives.
Amen?
Praise God for salvation.
Praise God that he seals us and keeps us by the power of God.
Amen.
But number two, an urgency for the lost.
Judgment is coming.
Like we have never seen.
But you know who else is coming?
Jesus.
Even so come, Lord Jesus.
But hezbound us closed over this place.